In July of 1911,
في يوليو 1911،
a 35-year-old Yale graduate and professor set out from his rainforest camp
انطلق أحد خريجي جامعة ييل ذو 35 عاما، وهو أيضا بروفسور، من مخيمه في الغابة المطيرة
with his team.
رفقة فريقه.
After climbing a steep hill
بعد تسلق تلة شديدة الانحدار
and wiping the sweat from his brow,
ومَسْحِ العرق عن جبينه،
he described what he saw beneath him.
وصف ما شاهده في الأسفل.
He saw rising from the dense rainforest foliage
لقد رأى متاهة مذهلة من الهياكل المتشابكة
this incredible interlocking maze of structures
تتصاعد من أوراق الشجر الكثيف للغابة المطيرة
built of granite,
وهي مبنية من الجرانيت،
beautifully put together.
و مجموعة مع بعضها بشكل جميل.
What's amazing about this project
المدهش حول هذا المشروع
is that it was the first funded by National Geographic,
هو أنه كان أول مشروع مموَّل من قبل ناشيونال جيوغرافيك،
and it graced the front cover of its magazine in 1912.
ولقد زيَّن الغلاف الأمامي لمجلتها في عام 1912.
This professor used state-of-the-art photography equipment
استخذم هذا البروفسور أحدث أجهزة التصوير
to record the site,
لتسجيل الموقع،
forever changing the face of exploration.
مغيّرًا بذلك وجه الاستكشاف إلى الأبد.
The site was Machu Picchu,
كان هذا الموقع هو مدينة "ماتشو بيتشو"،
discovered and explored by Hiram Bingham.
التي اكتشفها واستكشفها "هيرام بينغهام".
When he saw the site, he asked,
عندما رأى الموقع، تساءل:
"This is an impossible dream.
"هذا حلم مستحيل.
What could it be?"
ماذا يمكن أن يكون؟"
So today,
إذن اليوم،
100 years later,
بعد 100 سنة،
I invite you all on an incredible journey with me,
أدعوكم جميعا في رحلة رائعة معي،
a 37-year-old Yale graduate and professor.
خريجة جامعة ييل وأستاذة جامعية بالغة من العمر 37 عاما،
(Cheers)
(هتاف)
We will do nothing less than use state-of-the-art technology
لن نفعل ما هو أقل من استخدام أحدث الأجهزة التكنولوجية
to map an entire country.
لرسم خريطة بلد بأكمله.
This is a dream started by Hiram Bingham,
هذا حلم بدأ مع هيرام بينغهام،
but we are expanding it to the world,
ولكن نحن الآن بصدد نشره للعالم،
making archaeological exploration more open, inclusive,
بجعل التنقيب الأثري مفتوحا أكثر وشاملا،
and at a scale simply not previously possible.
ببساطة على نطاق لم يكن ممكنا في السابق.
This is why I am so excited
هذا هو سبب كوني متحمسة جدا
to share with you all today
لأشارككم جميعا اليوم
that we will begin the 2016 TED Prize platform
أننا سنبدأ منصة جائزة TED لعام 2016
in Latin America,
في أمريكا اللاتينية،
more specifically Peru.
وتحديدا في "بيرو".
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.
We will be taking Hiram Bingham's impossible dream
سنقوم بأخذ الحلم المستحيل ل"هيرام بينغهام"
and turning it into an amazing future
وسنحوَّله إلى مستقبل مدهش
that we can all share in together.
بإمكاننا جميعا أن نتشاركه معا.
So Peru doesn't just have Machu Picchu.
إن "بيرو" لا تحتوي على " ماتشو بيتشو" فقط .
It has absolutely stunning jewelry,
بل لديها مجوهرات مذهلة للغاية،
like what you can see here.
مثل ما ترونه هنا.
It has amazing Moche pottery of human figures.
لديها فخار موتشي مذهل لشخصيات بشرية.
It has the Nazca Lines
لديها خطوط نازكا
and amazing textiles.
ومنسوجات مذهلة.
So as part of the TED Prize platform,
إذن وكجزء من منصة جائزة TED،
we are going to partnering with some incredible organizations,
سنعقد شراكة مع بعض المنظمات الرائعة،
first of all with DigitalGlobe, the world's largest provider
أولها "ديجيتال جلوب" ، أكبر مزود في العالم
of high-resolution commercial satellite imagery.
للصورالتجارية عالية الدقة من تصوير الأقمار الصناعية.
They're going to be helping us build out
سيقومون بمساعدتنا لتوسيع
this amazing crowdsourcing platform they have.
منصة التعهيد الجماعي المذهلة التي يمتلكونها.
Maybe some of you used it
ربما استخذمها البعض منكم
with the MH370 crash and search for the airplane.
في حادث MH370 والبحث عن الطائرة.
Of course, they'll also be providing us with the satellite imagery.
وبطبيعة الحال، سوف يوفرون لنا أيضا صور الأقمار الصناعية.
National Geographic will be helping us with education and of course exploration.
ستقوم ناشيونال جيوغرافيك بمساعدتنا في المعرفة والاستكشاف طبعا.
As well, they'll be providing us with rich content for the platform,
وأيضا، سيقومون بتزويدنا بمحتوى غني من أجل المنصة،
including some of the archival imagery like you saw at the beginning of this talk
بما في ذلك بعض الصور الأرشيفية مثل التي رأيتم في بداية هذه المحادثة
and some of their documentary footage.
وبعض لقطات فيلمهم الوثائقي.
We've already begun to build and plan the platform,
لقد بدأنا فعليّا في البناء والتخطيط للمنصة،
and I'm just so excited.
وأنا فقط جد متحمسة .
So here's the cool part.
حسنا ها هو الجزء الرائع.
My team, headed up by Chase Childs,
قام فريقي، بقيادة "تشيس تشايلدز"،
is already beginning to look at some of the satellite imagery.
بالبدأ فعليّا بالنظر إلى بعض من صور الأقمار الصناعية.
Of course, what you can see here is 0.3-meter data.
بالطبع، ما يمكنكم رؤيته هنا هو بيانات 0.3 متر.
This is site called Chan Chan in northern Peru.
هذا موقع يسمى "تشان تشان" في شمال "بيرو".
It dates to 850 AD.
ويرجع تاريخه إلى عام 850 بعد الميلاد.
It's a really amazing city, but let's zoom in.
إنها مدينة مذهلة حقا، ولكن دعونا نقوم بتكبيرها.
This is the type and quality of data that you all will get to see.
هذه هي نوعية وجودة البيانات التي سوف تحصلون جميعا على فرصة رؤيتها.
You can see individual structures, individual buildings.
يمكنكم رؤية هياكل فردية ومباني فردية.
And we've already begun to find previously unknown sites.
ولقد بدأنا بالفعل في إيجاد مواقع لم تكن معروفة سابقا.
What we can say already is that as part of the platform,
ما يمكننا قوله هو أنه و كجزء من المنصة،
you will all help discover thousands of previously unknown sites,
ستساعدون جميعا في اكتشاف الآلاف من المواقع غير المعروفة من قبل،
like this one here,
مثل هذا،
and this potentially large one here.
وهذا ذو الاحتمال الأكبر.
Unfortunately, we've also begun to uncover large-scale looting at sites,
للأسف، بدأنا أيضا بالكشف عن عمليات نهب في المواقع وذلك على نطاق واسع،
like what you see here.
مثل ما ترونه هنا.
So many sites in Peru are threatened,
والعديد من المواقع في "بيرو" مهددة،
but the great part is that all of this data
ولكن الجزء الأروع هو أن كل هذه البيانات
is going to be shared with archaeologists on the front lines
سوف تتم مشاركتها مع علماء آثار قياديين
of protecting these sites.
لحماية هذه المواقع.
So I was just in Peru, meeting with their Minister of Culture
لقد كنت مؤخرا في "بيرو"، في لقاء مع وزير الثقافة الخاص بهم
as well as UNESCO.
ومنظمة اليونسكو كذلك.
We'll be collaborating closely with them.
سوف نتعاون بشكل وثيق معهم.
Just so you all know,
لعلمكم فقط ،
the site is going to be in both English and Spanish,
فإن الموقع سيكون باللغتين الإنجليزية والإسبانية معا،
which is absolutely essential to make sure
وهذا أمر ضروري للغاية للتأكد
that people in Peru and across Latin America can participate.
من أن الناس في "بيرو" وفي جميع أنحاء أمريكا اللاتينية يمكنهم المشاركة.
Our main project coprincipal investigator is the gentleman you see here,
المدير المشارك لمجموعتنا البحثية هو الرجل الذي ترونه هنا،
Dr. Luis Jaime Castillo,
الدكتور لويس خايمي كاستيلو،
professor at Catholic University.
بروفيسور في الجامعة الكاثوليكية.
As a respected Peruvian archaeologist and former vice-minister,
كعالم آثار محترم من "بيرو" ونائب وزير سابق
Dr. Castillo will be helping us coordinate and share the data with archaeologists
سيساعدنا الدكتور كاستيلو للتنسيق وتبادل البيانات مع علماء الآثار
so they can explore these sites on the ground.
حتى يتمكنوا من استكشاف هذه المواقع على الأرض.
He also runs this amazing drone mapping program,
وهو يدير أيضا برنامجا مذهلا لرسم الخرائط جويّا ،
some of the images of which you can see behind me here and here.
يمكنكم رؤية بعض من هذ الصور ورائي هنا وهنا.
And this data will be incorporated into the platform,
وسوف تُدرج هذه البيانات في المنصة،
and also he'll be helping to image some of the new sites you help find.
وهو سيساعد أيضا في تصوير بعض المواقع الجديدة التي ستساعدون في اكتشافها.
Our on-the-ground partner
شريكنا المباشر في الموقع
who will be helping us with education, outreach,
والذي سيساعدنا في المعرفة والتوعية،
as well as site preservation components,
وكذا مكونات المحافظة على الموقع،
is the Sustainable Preservation Initiative,
هي "مبادرة المحافظة المستدامة"،
led by Dr. Larry Coben.
برئاسة الدكتور لاري كوبن.
Some of you may not be aware
البعض منكم قد لا يكون على علم
that some of the world's poorest communities
بأن بعض أفقر مجتمعات العالم
coexist with some of the world's most well-known archaeological sites.
تتعايش مع بعض من المواقع الأثرية الأكثر شهرة في العالم.
What SPI does
ما تقوم به هذه المبادرة هو
is it helps to empower these communities,
المساعدة على تمكين هذه المجتمعات،
in particular women,
وخاصة النساء،
with new economic approaches and business training.
وذلك باستخذام مقاربات اقتصادية جديدة والتدريب على الأعمال التجارية.
So it helps to teach them to create beautiful handicrafts
إذن فهي تساعد على تعليمهم لصنع منتوجات يدوية جميلة
which are then sold on to tourists.
يتم بيعها إلى السياح.
This empowers the women to treasure their cultural heritage
هذا يمكَّن النساء لتقدير تراثهم الثقافي
and take ownership of it.
والحصول على ملكيته.
I had the opportunity to spend some time with 24 of these women
لقد أتيحت لي الفرصة لقضاء بعض الوقت مع 24 من هؤلاء النساء
at a well-known archaeological site called Pachacamac, just outside Lima.
في موقع أثري معروف يسمى "باتشاكاماك"، خارج "ليما".
These women were unbelievably inspiring,
هؤلاء النسوة كن مُلهِمات بشكل لا يصدق،
and what's great is that SPI will help us transform communities
والعظيم هو أن تلك المبادرة ستساعدنا على تحويل المجتمعات
near some of the sites that you help to discover.
المتواجدة بالقرب من بعض المواقع التي ستساعدون على اكتشافها.
Peru is just the beginning.
إن "بيرو" هي مجرد بداية.
We're going to be expanding this platform to the world,
نحن في طريقنا إلى توسيع هذه المنصة إلى العالم،
but already I've gotten thousands of emails
ولكنني قد توصلت بآلاف رسائل البريد الإلكتروني
from people all across the world -- professors, educators, students,
من أشخاص في جميع أنحاء العالم - أساتذة ومعلمين وطلاب
and other archaeologists -- who are so excited to help participate.
وعلماء آثار آخرون - والذين هم متحمسون جدا للمشاركة.
In fact, they're already suggesting amazing places for us to help discover,
في الواقع، لقد اقترحوا علينا حتى الآن أماكن مدهشة لكي نساعد على اكتشافها،
including Atlantis.
بما في ذلك "أتلانتيس".
I don't know if we're going to be looking for Atlantis,
أنا لا أعرف ما إذا كنا ستبحث عن "أتلانتيس"،
but you never know.
لكن من يدري؟
So I'm just so excited to launch this platform.
وبالتالي فأنا متحمسة جدا لإطلاق هذه المنصة.
It's going to be launched formally by the end of the year.
سيتم إطلاقها رسميا بحلول نهاية هذا العام.
And I have to say,
ويجب أن أقول،
if what my team has already discovered in the past few weeks are any indication,
أنه وإذا كان ما قد اكتشفه فريقي في الأسابيع القليلة الماضية مؤشرا،
what the world discovers is just going to be beyond imagination.
فإن ما سيكتشفه العالم سيكون أبعد من الخيال.
Make sure to hold on to your alpacas.
تأكدوا من التمسك بالألبكة الخاص بكم.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.